Guide to the Alexander Jackson Davis Architectural Drawing Collection 1827-1884 PR 16
New-York Historical Society
- Rutherford, John House "North east." graphite UL; "Garden front Rutherford" graphite LR (Item 515)
  see also drawings #514, 516, 526, 531-534
- Rutherford, John House "north?" graphite LC (Item 516)
  see also drawings #514, 515, 526, 531-534
- Rutherford, John House "Principal floor." ink UL (Item 526)
  see also drawings #514, 515, 516, 531-534
- Saint Mark-in-the-Bowery Church, tower "St. Mark's. N.Y." ink LL (Item 211)
  remodeling, not executed, Peck, Alexander Jackson Davis, 109; build in 1799, steeple 1828, AIA Guide to NYC, 3rd ed., 166-167; see also #228
- Saint Thomas Church (Item 511)
  study of ornament of the interior of St. Thomas Church from chancel to left rear central area; see also drawing #511A
- Saint Thomas Church "St. THOMAS CHURCH. Broadway 1827" ink LC (Item 511A)
  view from rear towards east end; see also drawing #511
- School "School" watercolor MC (Item 320 recto)
  WM: JWhatman 1868. inscr: detilas of this plans which are drawn double this scale, address "Invention" No. 703 W 11th St. The plan requires explana-
- School "Rear Elevation" MC ink (Item 320 verso)
- "Second Story" ink, graphite, BM (Item 292)
- Sedgewick, Charles B. [sketch plans] (Item 366 a recto)
  Later rear addition by another architect, demonlished 1962
- Sedgewick, Charles B. "Geneological Table of Sedgwick" (Item 366 a verso)
- Sedgewick, Charles B. [Geneological Table] (Item 366 recto)
- Sedgewick, Charles B. [Geneological Table of Sedgwick Family with graphite doodles] (Item 366 b verso)
- Sedgwick, Charles B. Villa "Chas. B. Sedgwick Syracusa" graphite UL-ML (Item 159h)
  no evidence of execution, Peck, Alexander Jackson Davis, 115; see alos drawings #159 a-g
- Sedgwick, Charles B., House "End" (Item 159)
  see 159a-e, g
- Sedgwick, Charles B., House "1845 Cottage at Syracuse. Chas. B. Sedgwick," ink graphite BR (Item 159g)
  see 159 a-f
- Sedgwick, Charles B., House "Second Story C. B. Sedgwick 1845" ink, graphite UR (Item 159e)
  see 159 a-d, f-g, drawing reworked in places, partial plan in graphite on verso
- Sedgwick, Charles B., House [Main Floor Plan] (Item 159)
  see 159 a-c, e-g
- Sedgwick, Charles B., House "Section A to B No. 2" ink, graphite BM (Item 159b)
  see also 159a, c-g
- Sedgwick, Charles B., House "Dwilling erected at Syracuse, N. Y. in 1845 for Chas. B. Sedgewick [sic] by A. J. Davis Artc. Rear" ink, graphite BL-BR (Item 159a)
  see also 159 b-g
- Sedgwick, Charles B., House "Basement Drawing No. 1 Sedgwick, Chas. B. Sedgewick Syracuse. N.Y." ink, graphite BR (Item 159c)
  see also 159a-b, d-g, portions of image reworked
- Shotwell, Jacob R. House "Design. Shotwell" graphite MR (Item 166 verso)
  house and coach house, demolished, Peck, Alexander Jackson Davis, 116; see also drawing #170
- Shotwell, Jacob R. House (Item 170 recto)
  house and coach house, demolished, Peck, Alexander Jackson Davis, 116; see also #166 verso
- Sibley, Mark H. House "Plan for Mark H. Sibley, Canadaigua N.Y. Nov. 1835" ink BL (Item 290)
  Canandaigua (N.Y
- Simple country house Study for a Simple Country House (Item 564)
  Probably the original for the wood engraving published in the "Horticulturist" and Downing's "Architecture of Country Houses."
- Small cottage, or gate house "No. 2, First Floor Plan Small Cottage or Gate house" ink, graphite BL-BR (Item 273g)
- Smith, J. V. C. House (Item 285)
- Smith, Joscelyn House "Smith. Joscelyn, Esq." (Item 89)
- Specifications in letterpress for brick-layer "Brick-layer." NA UL (Item 556)
  see also #556a-g; double page
- Specifications in letterpress for conditions "Conditions for the performance of the several Works in the respective Trades, as set forth in, and according to the accompanying SPECIFICATIO (Item 556a)
  see also #556b-g; double page recto-verso
- Specifications in letterpress for mason "Mason." NA UL (Item 556c)
- Specifications in letterpress for plasterer and carpenter "Plasterer."first page, NA ML; "Carpenter." second page, NA UL (Item 556e)
- Specifications in letterpress for specifications and excavator "SPECIFICATION OF THE MATERIALS AND WORKS REQUIRED FOR BUILDING A DWELLING HOUSE" first page, NA UC; "Excavator." second page, NA UL (Item 556b)
- Specifications in letterprints for carpenter (Item 556)
- Specifications in letterprints for plumber, glazier, painter, bell hanger "Plumber." first page, NA ML; "Glazier." NA UL; "Painter." NA ML; "Bell Hanger." NA LL (Item 556g)
  see also #556a-f; double page
- St. Mark's Church "Side Elevation" "Longitudinal Section" watercolor, graphite CM, BM (Item 228)
- State capitol "For a State Capitol" ink UR (Item 319 c)
  inscr.: cent. vaults. Order, Doric, 50 ft. high. Corinthian 76, columns 6 ft." UR ink "First Floor C." UR ink
- State capitol, unidentified "Oblong Plan No 3" watercolor UL; "Plan of Basement or First Floor Section South" watercolor, CL to CR. (Item 319b)
  BM center of paper longer dimension. CM separate sheet collaged onto recto, 4 5/16 x 4 3/4", erasures, reworked in some areas probably by Davis
- State capitol, unidentified "Plan of Prncipal Floor Center 100 by 300 Length 500" watercolor, CL - CR (Item 319a)
  Paper longer dimension BM; drawing collaged on recto CM 6 1/4 x 6 1/2"; noticeable erasures--probably by Davis; see also 319b
- Steward House "Steward" graphite BM (Item 294)
- Studies for Bowery church (Item 236a)
- Studies for Bowery church "Three Double Houses and Ch." ink, graphite LC (Item 236b)
- Studies for Bowery church "Principal Story" ink, graphite LC (Item 236c)
- Studies for Bowery residence (Item 247a recto)
  watermark ..IN & Co
- Studies for Bowery residence "Church with 2 Dwellings" ink, graphite UL "4 Large Dwelling" ink graphite UR (Item 247a verso)
- Studies for Bowery residence and church (Item 247e)
- "STUDIO" graphite LC "STUDIO" graphite LC (Item 463 recto)
- "STUDIO" verso, graphite LC (Item 463 verso)
- Study for a Merchants Exchange "Invention - Marble Shafts - Iron Tiles" graphite UR (Item 301a)
  see drawing #307a
- Study for spacing columns "Study for Spacing Columns 6 or 10 8 would bring one in line of door." graphite UR (Item 237)
- Swiss rural residence, farmer's house "Switz. Rural Res. No. 5" graphite UL; "ENLARGED FARMER'S HOUSE. SHINGLE." ink and NA ML-MR (Item 157)
  alterations on a page from Davis Book "Rural Residences"
- Tappan Store "Tappan's Store" (Item 20)
- Tenement house competition "Tenement House Monumental Inscription" (Item 267b)
  verso: announcement National Academy of Design 1876, 55th Annual Exhibition
- Tenement house competition (Item 267a recto)
- Tenement house competition (Item 267a verso)
- The New-York Historical Society "Historical Society" watercolor, ink wash, ink, graphite, UM (Item 049 verso)
  see 49 recto; Vail, Knickerbocker birthday, 119; not executed
- The New-York Historical Society "Historical Society A Study" "Library & Collections of the N.Y. Historical Society." ink, graphite UR (Item 049 recto)
  see 49 verso; not executed, Peck, Alexander Jackson Davis, 119; Vail, Knickerbocker Birthday, 119
- Title page for port folio (Item 069j)
  the inscriptions refer to some of Davis projects for residences
- Town house, Etruscan, unidentified (Item 245 recto)
- Town house, four story, unidentified (Item 405)
  see also drawing #400
- Town house, three-story, unidentified "CHARACTER, NO. IV." ink UC (Item 557)
- Town house, unidentified (Item 245 verso)
  plan for 245 recto
- Town house, unidentified "Section" watercolor, graphite BM (Item 255 verso)
- Town house, unidentified "Front of Corner House 52 Section" watercolor, graphite BL-BR (Item 254)
- Town house, unidentified "Basement for a town-house." ink wash LL-LR (Item 409)
- Town house, unidentified (Item 411)
- Town house, unidentified "CITY CORNER LOT. ELEVATION OF SIDE> FRONT ON END." ink LL-LR (Item 172)
- Town house, unidentified (Item 179 recto)
- Town house, unidentified (Item 179 verso)
- Town house, Winslow Residence? (Item 156c)
  for Winslow Residence, see drawings #156a-b
- Townhouse, unidentified, probably for C. A. Davis (Item 243a verso)
- Trumbull Gallery / Exchange Windows (Item 364 recto)
  Manhattan (New York, N.Y.), New Haven (Conn.)
- Trumbull Gallery / Exchange Windows (Item 364 recto)
- Tuscan portico "Tuscan portico" graphite UR (Item 105)
  Paterson (N.J.)
  graphite perspective drawing of classical temples in the pediment.
- Unidentified monument (Item 580a)
  see also drawings #580b-c
- Unidentified monument (Item 580b)
  see also drawings #580a-c
- Unidentified monument (Item 580c)
  see also drawings #580a-b
- Unidentified residence with octogonal room (Item 446)
  alterations visible; "Mrs. H.'s room." indicated, ink, LR
- Unidentified residence with octogonal room (Item 569)
  see also drawing #446
- Unidentified residence with semi-circular entrance portico (Item 562 verso)
- Unidentified residences in the shape of a Y (Item 551 recto)
- Unidentified semi-circular residence (Item 445)
- Unidentified semi-circular residence (Item 445)
- Unidentified seven-story residence (Item 447 recto)
  see verso
- Unidentified seven-story residence (Item 447 verso)
- Unidentified seven-story residence (Item 568 recto)
  see also drawings #447 recto and verso
- Unidentified seven-story residence "BED-ROOM FLOOR" ink UC (Item 568 verso)
  see also verso and drawings #447 recto and verso
- Untitled (Item 310)
- Vanderlyn Rotunda "Rotunda - Chambers - Street" (Item 024b)
- Vanderlyn Rotunda "VANDERLYN ROTUNDA. N. YORK PARK." ink LC (Item 23)
  title page for "Views of the Publi Buildings in the City of New York, 1827, Peck, Alexander Jackson Davis, 31-31
- Vanderlyn Rotunda, Title Page of Book of A. J. Davis's views of public buildings "Views of the Public Buildings in the City of New York Correctly Drawn on Stone by A. J. Davis and Published by A. Imbert Lithographer no. 79 (Item 25)
- Vanderlyn Rotunda, Title page of book of A. J. Davis views of public buildings "Views of the Public Buildings in the City of New York correctly drawn on stone by A. J. Davis. Printed & Published by A. Imbert Lithographer (Item 24)
- Villa with rotund apartments "Study for a Villa with Rotund apartments" ink, graphite UR (Item 297)
- Villa, Americanized Greek style "AMERICANIZED ROMAN." graphite LC (Item 136)
  see also drawing #137
- Villa, Americanized Greek style "Design No. 3." ink LC (Item 137)
  see also drawing #136
- Villa, Etruscan "ETRUSCAN. Design for a Small Cottage." ink MC (Item 145 recto)
  see also drawing #144, 138a-b, 112
- Villa, Etruscan "ETRUSCAN." ink LC (Item 138a)
- Villa, Etruscan, unidentified "[Etruscan-]" LR (Item 176)
- Villa, Gothic, unidentified (Item 274e)
  residence similar to Belmead, Philip St. George Cocke, 1845-1848, see Peck, Alexander Jackson Davis, 112; see #274a-d
- Villa, Grecian "Simplest Form for the Grecian Villa" ink, graphite BL-BR (Item 298a recto)
  see 298b for verso, WM
- Villa, Grecian "South front" ink, graphite BM (Item 298b verso)
- Villa, Greek "Greek" ink, graphite CM (Item 293)
- Villa, Greek, unidentified "GREEK." ink LC (Item 140)
- Villa, Palmyran, unidentified "PALMYRAN" watercolor MC (Item 153)
- Villa, Palmyrean "Palmyrean No.2" watercolor, ink, graphite CM (Item 291)
  two pieces of paper joined together
- Villa, Tudor "TUDOR VILLA." ink wash ML (Item 166 recto)
- Villa, Tudor, unidentified (Item 152)
  drawn on an erased drawing
- Villa, unidentified (Item 571)
  the signature has probably been scratched out
- Villa, unidentified "Highland Villa" graphite UL (Item 154a)
  see also drawing #154b
- Villa, unidentified "Highland Villa" graphite UR (Item 154b)
  see also drawing #154a
- Villa, unidentified (Item 402)
- Villa, unidentified (Item 384)
- Village chapel "No. 2 Plan for a Village Chapel. by Alex'r J. Davis" ink graphite (Item 229)
- Village Chapel and School "Plan" ink, ink wash BM (Item 214b)
  hinged to 214a measures 14 1/4 x 11 5/16". J. Davies notes for Isabelle Donaldson, model for village schoolhouse in "Rural Residences"
- Village Chapel and School "Front For a Village Chapel and School. The Lord by knowledge hath founded the earth; By understanding hath he established the heavens" ink wa (Item 214a)
  hinged to 214b measures 14 6/16 x 11 1/4". J. Davies notes for Isabelle Donaldson, model for village schoolhouse in "Rural Residences"
- Village Chapel and School "Design for a Model School House"MC (Item 335 a)
  demolished, for Isabella Donaldson (wife of Robert Donaldson who owned Blithewood), lithograph for Rural Residences
- Village Chapel and School "Section From A to B" (Item 335 b)
- Village Chapel and School "Design for a School House" (Item 335 c)
- Village Chapel and School (Item 335 d)
- Village chapel, unidentified (Item 215 recto)
- Village church (Item 224b)
  see also drawings #224a-c, 225
- Village church "DESIGN FOR A VILLAGE CHURCH." ink MC (Item 224a)
  see also drawings #224b-c, 225
- Village church "DESIGN FOR A VILLAGE CHURCH." NA MC (Item 224c)
  see also drawings #224a-b, 225, alterations in graphite visible
- Village church, study "VILLAGE CHURCH, A STUDY." ink wash, ink LC (Item 216)
  see also drawing #214a-b, 215 recto, 217, 218a-b, 219
- Village Lyceum "Village. Lyceum. Lower Floor. Persepctive View in Cosmorama." (Item 336)
- Waddell, William Coventry H. House, Murray Hill, envelope "Waddell Villa. Photograph of Prints with mss. description" ink UL-UC (Item [629])
  demolished 1856 due to the leveling of 5th Avenue, Peck, ALexander Jackson Davis, 111; see also #[630]
- Waddell, William Coventry H. House, Murray Hill, manuscript description "No. 132-" ink UC (Item [630])
  6 pages description; demolished 1856 due to the leveling of 5th Avenue, Peck, Alexander Jackson Davis, 111; see also #[629]
- Waddell, William Coventry H. Residence, Murray Hill "SUBURBAN GOTHIC VILLA, MURRAY HILL, N. Y. CITY. RESIDENCE OF W. C. H. WADDELL, ESQ. 5th Avenue, between 37 & 38th Street." NA ML-MR (Item 275n.26)
  demolished 1856 due to the leveling of Fifth Avenue, Peck, Alexander Jackson Davis, 111; bound with pages from "Rural Residences"
- Wadsworth, William Wolcott House "Wm. W. Wadsworth" (Item 371 recto)
  Geneseo (N.Y.)
- Wadsworth, William Wolcott House [Plans] (Item 371 verso)
- Wadsworth, William Wolcott House [Plans] (Item 372 recto)
  Not executed
- Wadsworth, William Wolcott House [Parial Plan] (Item 372 verso)
- Wadsworth, William Wolcott House [Plans] (Item 372 recto)
- Walsh House "End Walsh, Albany" watercolor ink, graphite (Item 286a)
- Walsh House "Principal Story. Walsh. Albany" watercolor graphite UR (Item 286b)
- Welles, H. D. House "Preliminary study for Welles." ink UR; "Study on Wells" graphite MR (Item 129)
  Hartford (Conn.)
  apparently not executed, Peck, Alezxander Jackson Davis, 115; see also drawing #81
- Wells, H. D. Residence "Preliminary Study for H. D. Welles; Hartford, Ct. 1851." ink UC-UR (Item 81)
  apparently not executed, Peck, Alexander Jackson Davis, 115; see also drawing #129
- White Sulpher Spings Hotel "Principal floor, 2. for a Hotel Wh Sulph Sp. Va" ink and graphite LR (Item 308)
  West Virginia
  Originally White Sulpher Springs in VA, now WV; commission for new hotel, additions and bath house, not executed, design both classical and gothic
- White Sulpher Springs Hotel "Principal Floor. B. for a Hotel White Sulpher Springs" ink, graphite LR (Item 299)
  Originally VA, additions, new hotel and bath house in classical and gothic styles, not executed.
- Wier, Andrew Villa "Cellar and Foundations. No. 1." ink UC (Item 146)
  Norfolk (Va.)
  see also 143a-g
- Wier, Andrew Villa "V. FRONT ELEVATION." ink LC (Item 143a)
  see also #143a-g, 146
- Wier, Andrew Villa "End Elevation. No. 6." ink LC (Item 143b)
  see also drawings #143a-g, 146
- Wier, Andrew Villa "Long Section. No." ink LC (Item 143c)
- Wier, Andrew Villa "Attic and Roof. No. 4." ink LC (Item 143)
- Wier, Andrew Villa "Plan of the principal floor." ink UC (Item 143e)
- Wier, Andrew Villa "Varied plan." ink UR (Item 143)
- Wier, Andrew Villa "Second story. No. 3." ink UC (Item 143g)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Section West end No. 8" (Item 253v)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Looking Glass for Lodge. Wildmont. Tower Window" ink CM (Item 253a)
  A. J. Davis's summer lodge, later expanded c. 1878.
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Dining" graphite CM (Item 253d verso)
  A. J. Davis's summer lodge, later expanded c. 1878. In wrapper "Wildmont First Lodge not wanted for new lodge"
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253k verso)
  A. J. Davis's summer lodge, later expanded 1878. In wrapper: "Wildmont - First Lodge not wanted for new lodge."
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Skylight. north wing. Wildm't" graphite CL-CR (Item 253c verso)
- Wildmont - First Lodge Calculations (Item 253d recto)
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253e verso)
  A. J. Davis's summer lodge, later expanded 1878. In wrapper "Wildmont First Lodge not wanted for new lodge"
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253e recto)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Screen At Wildmont Lodge" graphite UR (Item 253i recto)
  "A. J. Davis's summer lodge, later expanded 1878. In wrapper: "Wildmont - First Lodge not wanted for new lodge."
- Wildmont - First Lodge "14 Beams over Dining room" (Item 253)
  "A. J. Davis's summer lodge, later expanded 1878. In wrapper: "Wildmont - First Lodge not wanted for new lodge." on verso: "American con't
- Wildmont - First Lodge "14 Beams over Parlor 2d sotry floor" ink BM (Item 253g)
  "A. J. Davis's summer lodge, later expanded 1878. In wrapper: "Wildmont - First Lodge not wanted for new lodge." draft of will on verso
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Basement No. 1. Old House" ink, graphite (Item 253h)
  "A. J. Davis's summer lodge, later expanded 1878. In wrapper: "Wildmont - First Lodge not wanted for new lodge." WM: JWhatman 1868
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253q verso)
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253i verso)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "And he shall direct thy paths in all thy ways acknowledge him" graphite BR-UR (Item 253u verso)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Cove molding in west chamber ceiling" graphite UL (Item 253j verso)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Section Library and plan. North End" ink, graphite BL-BR (Item 253k recto)
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253l)
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253m)
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253n recto)
  A. J. Davis's summer lodge, later expanded 1878. In wrapper: "Wildmont - First Lodge not wanted for new lodge." 11 x 14" paper folded 1/2.
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Flora's Dict." ink UM (Item 253o recto)
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253o verso)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Front door" graphite BM (Item 253p)
- Wildmont - First Lodge [unidentifiable subject matter] (Item 253q recto)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Lodge Study north end" graphite UL-UR (Item 253r)
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253s)
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253t recto)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "North End" graphite UL (Item 253t verso)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Section North End Wildmont lodge looking east" ink, graphite UM (Item 253t recto)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Things yet to do at lodge" (Item 253c recto)
- Wildmont - First Lodge "Section of Library looking south. Looking North" ink, graphite CM, CM (Item 253j recto)
- Wildmont - First Lodge (Item 253n verso)
- Wildmont - First Lodge, Wadell Window/ Wildmont Window "Wadell Bay wnidow sahs 22 by 112 glass 16 x 26 Built into bay at Wildmont." ink, graphite UR (Item 253b)
- Winslow Residence "Study for Winslow." ink LL (Item 156a recto)
  unidentified project; see also verso and #156b
- Winslow Residence "Study for Winslow." ink and graphite LR (Item 156a verso)
  unidentified project; see also recto and #156b
- Winslow Residence "CORNER LOT." watercolor LR (Item 156a verso)
  collage; unidentified project; see also #156a recto-verso
- View Through a Monumental Greek Portico (Item 575)
- "12. Window over Drawing room bay. Window over front porch." (Item 251a)
- unidentified project (Item 276c)
- unidentified project (Item 276)
- unidentified project (Item 250)
  similar to early 300 series drawings, wm: "JWhatman 1868"
- unidentified project (Item 001c)
- unidentified project (Item 204)
- unidentified project (Item [605])
- unidentified project (Item 452)